<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>To the King both Houses of Parliament friends remember, you must all come to judgement for the one everlasting judge from whom there is no appeal to any other : who is no respecter of persons, he is the one judge of the conscience.</title>
            <author>Livingstone, Patrick, 1634?-1694.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 13KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 1 1-bit group-IV TIFF page image.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B09418</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">64551366</idno>
  <idno type="VID">184640</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240865920</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing L2606A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R224391</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">64551366</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B09418)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 184640)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English Books, 1641-1700 ; 2869:6)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>To the King both Houses of Parliament friends remember, you must all come to judgement for the one everlasting judge from whom there is no appeal to any other : who is no respecter of persons, he is the one judge of the conscience.</title>
                  <author>Livingstone, Patrick, 1634?-1694.</author>
                  <author>England and Wales. Parliament.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>1 sheet ([1] p.).   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1670.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Signed at end: Patrick Livingstone.</note>
                  <note>Dated at end: London the 8th of the 9th month, 1670.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: Harvard University. Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="personal_name">Charles --  II, --  King of England, 1630-1685.</term>
               <term type="topical_term">Religion and politics --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term type="topical_term">Church and state --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term type="genre_form">Broadsides --  England --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2014-05 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-07 </date>
            <label>John Pas </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-07 </date>
            <label>John Pas</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:184640:1"/>
            <head>To the KING and both Houses of Parliament.</head>
            <p>FRiends Remember, You must all come to Judg<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ment b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>fore the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ne everlasting Judge from whom there is no Appeal to any other: who is no respecter of Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sons, he is the on<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>udge of the Conscience, All judgment in He<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>v n, and Earth is committed unto him, as ye love the good of your own Souls and outward pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sperity, Beware that you meddle not with his Prerogative, who is the judge of Conscience, who toucheth the Conscience and awakens it, and when the Consci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence is a wakened and trouble enters because of s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>se <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>f sin and tr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nsgression, All the Kings on Earth cannot quiet Conscience again, and seeing you cannot quiet Conscience, nor wound Conscience as to make sensibl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of sin, you had best not m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ddle to persecute any simply upon the matter of Conscience, for if by violence you make any sin, and do that which is against their Consciences, and if they be troubled for it you can<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ot give them peace, you cannot excuse them before God, therefore beware you force not People in matters of Conscience, least God in his wrath rise up in your own Consciences, and then you may come to see what it is to have a troubled Conscience: On King and those that in Parliament sit, be it known unto you all that it is the living God that hath troubled, and awakened our Consciences and made Us sensible of our sins that grieved the Lord, who by his power in Us hath wroug<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t in a mighty m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nner in th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> way of his judgments which were terrible to the man of sin in Us, and to us as we wer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> joyned to the sin, so we have known the terrors of the Lord, and his wrath hath burned in us because of sin, and in that day thou and all thy Parliam<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nt were far from Us to give Us any ease, or peace, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ut the Cry in Us vvas to the Lord that his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ye mig<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t not pitty, not his hand spare, nor his fire to cease until the sin and transgression was done away, wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ch caused the Lords displeasure, against us, and now the Lord hav<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ng appeared in Us in the way of his judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments whereby he hath purged many, and put an end to the Sin, and finished the transgression, and hath broug<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t in the everlasting Righteousness, and so by his own e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verlasting power he gath<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>red Us into many Assemblies in these Nations, and the Lord is mighty by his Spirit in our Ass mblies, the Lord has gathered us out of the War and strife, yea out of the cause o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> all War and strife, out of the Lusts of the flesh, into the love of his Truth, and his command is in Us, and to Us that we keep to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether in his power and that we forsake not our Assembling together, and the presence of the Lord is in the midst of Us, and we can call G<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Heaven and Earth to Record upon our Spirits that we intend nothing by our M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>tings but simply the Worship of God, We may n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t learn War any more with carnal Weapons, we may not hate our enemies, nor render evil for evil, we may not curse them that despitefully use Us, we may not d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>sire evil in our h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>arts against them, the Lord is a Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ness upon our Spi its that we h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ve not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>vil in our hearts against you, but we seek your good, and what do you mean by thus suffering Us to be abused, and beat, and our good<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> spoiled by your command, and our Meeting-hous<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s stopt up with violent men, would such p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oceedings conv<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nce Us if we were wrong? Nay surely, But be it known unto you that We have counted the Cost, the power of the Lord God is in the midst of Us, we are His, and He is our Por<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ion, and for his sake we suffer, and for no evil doing, the Lord is our R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>cord upon our spirits, its not for plotting, nor any evil doing, but simply b cause we cannot <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>rb<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ar the Ass mbling of our selves together, let the just witness of God answer for Us in all that ris<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> up against Us, what have we done, what can be justly laid to our cha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ge, have ye any thing against Us, but simply the matter▪ and m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nner of the wo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ship of our God, will you take upon you to judge our hearts, if nay, then is not the T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ee known by its Fruits, have not, and are not our fruits Holyness, and Righteousness, skiring forth in our lives and conversations, and in our Assemblies, and in our patient sufferings are not we ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifested to be a true people, and Worshippers of the living God, even by the very rage of the e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>emy against Us, in wicked people that abuse Us, from hence may not ye see that the World love Us n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t because we be not of the World, h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ve we used violence again, h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ve we rendred evil for evil, have we sought by a y carnal wea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon, or carnal way to deliver our selves, nay but we have committed our selves unto the Lord, and so have given up our selves willingly to suffer rath r then to sin, now judge who we are that are thus used, and who they are that use us thus, compare your proceedings ag<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>inst Us (an innocent people) with the proce<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ding<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of Christ and his Followers, against those that were wrong<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>, Christ would not suffer to destroy them that would not rec<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ive him, but we have received him, and y<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t you deal with Us far another way, then Christ dealt with them that would not receive him into their City though they denyed to receive him yet he would not have th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>m per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>secuted Christs command concerning them that would not obey his Church was to cast them out of his Church f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>llowship, but he never commanded to beat them, and abuse them, or spoil their goods as is done to Us, who haue received him, and are by him gathered into his everlasting power, now Christs followers had immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate Revelations, which you say you have not, Christs Church did not err in judging <hi>He eticks,</hi> they were <hi>Hereticks</hi> whom his Church judged then, and the true Church now may not proceed against <hi>Hereticks</hi> in another manner, they must not take another course with them then what th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ue Church took with them in former days, now we find <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ot th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> true Church proceeded against <hi>Hereticks</hi> by any carnal <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>rc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, as Imprisonment, banishment, b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aring, spoiling of their <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oods, but only Christs command al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows them to be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ut o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> from t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e church<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s fellowship, This was their proceedings who were guided by immedi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>te Revelatio<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s against <hi>Hereticks,</hi> or them that would not obey the church, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ut <hi>I</hi>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ay you do not claim to immediate Revela ions, nor to be guided by an infallible Spirit why then do you not consider it and lay it to heart; that ye may be mistak<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n and so persecute the innocent people of God under the name of <hi>Hereticks,</hi> as ever all p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>s<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>cut<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rs did, they never judged the people of God that were persecuted by t em to be inno<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ent, or to be the people of Go<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, though indeed they w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>re true, though accounted deceivers by them that were not true, so that you may look upon y<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ur p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>c edings against U<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> (an innocent people) to be far otherwise then the true chu ch s was against rea <hi>H reticks,</hi> and if <hi>Hereticks</hi> were to be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded against as you <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ve proc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eded against Us, that are no <hi>Hereticks</hi> but are true Worshippers of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> l ving Go<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>; yet you that p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oceed so ought to be in that which is infallibl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, that you mig<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t not mistake the p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ple of God, and persecute th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>m instead of <hi>Hereticks.</hi>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>herefore Oh King and Parliam<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nt consider what you do, for they are not the Kings Friends who counc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>l him to p rsecute any about the matters of worship. Let all sorts of People in th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>se N<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tions h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ve the lib<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rty of their Consc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences. Let every sort <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uild thems<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>lves publ c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>g H<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uses, and me<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t in publick, and maintain <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y one their own Minis<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ers, th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n that would qu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ckly gain the he<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ts o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> all sorts of pe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ple, to t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e King, and that wo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ld make the King strong in the hea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ts of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> pe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ple, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d it would ing<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ge t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>em from their hearts to serve the K<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ng, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> again I <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ay it is no good policy, n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ither are they the Kings friends that would councel him to any t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ing that might loosen, or withdraw the hearts of the Kings Su<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>jects from him, and they that councel the King to persecute p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ople their c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>cel leads to with<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>raw the hearts o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>is Subj<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>cts against him, for though we deny fighting, or h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>lping our selves by any carnal weapon, and though no persecution can never provoke Us to it, and though we l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ve our <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>emies and pray for our enemi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s, and so may not sight, y<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ther sorts of separate people holds it lawful to fight, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ow i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> they shall be suffered to meet in publick and maintain ever<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> one their own Ministers, that will b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> a good means to withdraw them from all private meetings, as to plot, yea it will be a good means to put out of their hearts discontent for from whence ris<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s all pl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ting but <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rom a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>isc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nt within, and to stop them from publ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ck Meetings is not this a ready way to Irritate them▪ and to put them upon the pain of disp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>? for it is a so<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e thing to oppress the Conscience, and you know that you cannot <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>each into t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e Consci<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nce, with any outward fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ce to turn it unto God, and to that w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ich is well p easing unto h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>m, and if you <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>now not this its very sad, and seeing it is so that God alo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e perswad s Consc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ence, leave every one to worship according to h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s perswasi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n, who knows not a better, for outward force will not bring any to know a better perswasion, Oh King and Parliament, its not pos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sible for you to bring all the peopl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> in t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ese Nations to worship in the Episcopal manner, outward force will not do it, therefore Oh King and b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>n Houses of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, consider what you have to do in this matter, and force none any more, but give all their liberty to Worship God in that way, then which they know no better, and then all sorts having liberty to worship publickly, then those Laws may stand in force against those that m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>t privately to plot, or that meet in any suspitious manner, for verily Friends, Its no good policy to stop publick Meetings, for they that mean to plot they may do it in private, but b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ing in publick then all are free to come in and to see what they are doing, for the stopping of publick Meetings occasions them to creep into corners and private places with their Meetings, and are occasions to beget discontent, envy, and prejudice in their minds, which is the ground of all plotting, but as for Us, we have suffered much both in <hi>Cromwells</hi> time, and in the Kings time, because we have been publick in our meetings, and however it be in your hearts to proce<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d with Us, y<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t we cannot be clear but to warn you and signifie unto you that while we have a being in that wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> God hath gathered Us into, and while our Tabernacles are upon Gods earth, we must worship God, we must not forbear the assembling of our selves together, what ever we may suffer for the same, if it should come to the laying down of our lives, we are the Lords, he hath chos<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>n Us, and he is our everlasting portion, whether we be in these Tabernacles, or removed, all shall work for the advancement of Truth, and good of all those that live in it to the end, vvhose faithful testimony, and sufferings in this Age shall preach through Ages to come, and their names shall be for a svveet <hi>Memorial</hi> among the Righteous in Ages to come, but the name of persecutors shall be had in Remembrance for evil, and vvill be an evil savour before people of succeeding Ages, and those that in this Age, vvho are true followers of the Lamb, and yet are persecuted under the names of deceiv<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rs shall be openly confessed to have been fa thful Followers of the Lamb in this Age by them of succeeding Ages, and th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> suffe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ings shall not be forgot, novv Oh King and Parliam<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nt, I have pretty vvell cl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ared my Conscience tovvard you.</p>
            <p>Wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ther you vvill hear, or forbear, my peace remains vvith me, vvhich none can take from me, but truly vvhen I heard of your Act and proceedings vvith the Innocent when I heard it in my own Nation of <hi>Scotland,</hi> it came very near me, and there was a true moving in my heart from the Lord to come to this City, and warn you which I have done in the counc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>l of God, and in love to your Souls, for your good it will be if you take it.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Friend Patrick Livingstone.</signed>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>London</hi>
                  <date>
                     <hi>the</hi> 8th <hi>of the</hi> 9th <hi>Month,</hi> 1670.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>